

# Charlotte Guertler, PhD

Senior Scientist Makerspace Associate Director Engineering Consultant



charlotteguertler.github.io



orcid: 0000-0003-0605-0239



LinkedIn: Charlotte Guertler charlotte.guertler@wustl.edu

### About me —

Charlotte is a mechanical engineer with experience in biomechanics, imaging, 3D bioprinting, material characterization, and project management. In addition to her brain biomechanics research, she is associate director of an engineering design makerspace, and a consultant for a biotech startup. Charlotte is excited to leverage her extensive research, design, and fabrication experience in biomedical industry.

### Skills —

#### R&D

Animal/human studies, MR imaging, MR elastography (MRE), diffusion tensor imaging (DTI), focused ultrasound, simulation and analysis of waves in solids

**Engineering Software** 

COMSOL, SolidWorks, Autodesk Fusion 360, Tinkercad

Programming Languages

MATLAB, Python, C++, Visual Basic, R, Mathematica, ExpressPCB, Arduino, LabView

Building, fabrication, prototyping 3D printing, laser cutting, machining & fabrication, welding, woodworking, sandblasting & powder coating, injection molding, vacuum forming

Publishing Software

Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, CorelDRAW, Inkscape, LaTeX

## Education

2019 PhD Washington University in St. Louis
Mechanical Engineering & Materials Science
Certificate in Imaging Science & Engineering

2017 MS Washington University in St. Louis

Mechanical Engineering & Materials Science

2014 BS Yale University Mechanical Engineering, ABET accredited

### Research and Work Experience

#### Postgraduate

2021-pres. Senior Scientist Washington University in St. Louis

Supervisor: Dr. Philip Bayly

Investigate tissue biomechanics and anisotropy using MR elastography

(MRE), ultrasound, and bioprinting

Responsibilities: conduct research, advise and supervise PhD, masters, and undergrduate students, manage projects, write publications and proposals

2021-pres. Associate Director

Spartan Light Metal Products Makerspace

Supervisor: Dr. Ruth J. Okamoto

Design and manage curriculum, vision, and operations for university-

wide makerspace

2021-pres. Engineering Consultant

DeepSight Technology

Supervisor: John Chong

Design, prototyping, and fabrication of ultrasound phantoms, demos,

and experimental setups

2019-21 Staff Research Scientist

Washington University in St. Louis

Supervisor: Dr. Philip Bayly

Investigate brain biomechanics and anisotropy using MR elastography

(MRE), ultrasound, and bioprinting

#### Graduate

2015-19 Graduate Student Researcher Washington University in St. Louis

Supervisor: Dr. Philip Bayly

Use MRE, ultrasound, and finite element analysis to assess mechanical

properties and anisotropy

2014 Graduate Student Researcher Washington University in St. Louis

Supervisor: Dr. Spencer Lake

Investigate the effects of hernia mesh on the mechanical properties of

the abdominal wall

#### Undergraduate

2011-14 Undergraduate Research Assistant Yale GRAB Lab

Supervisor: Dr. Aaron Dollar

Research on movement and grasp of human hand by modeling human

hand movements

2013 Engineering Intern Infineon Technologies

Supervisor: Andrea Stich

Member of pre-assembly team for semiconductors; clean room certified;

worked on one management project

2012 Engineering Intern Merck Research Laboratories

Supervisor: William Lee

Designed enclosure and setup of ligand identification system for Merck

research laboratory

## **Publications**

### \* authors contributed equally

2022 Estimation of the mechanical properties of a transversely isotropic material from shear wave fields via arti-

ficial neural networks

Hou Z\*, Guertler CA\*, Okamoto RJ, Chen H, Garbow JR, Kamilov US, Bayly PV

Journal of the Mechanical Behavior of Biomedical Materials | 10.1016/j.jmbbm.2021.105046

A heterogenous, time harmonic, nearly incompressible transverse isotropic finite element brain simulation

for MR elastography

McGarry M, Van Houten E, Guertler C, Okamoto R, Smith D, Sowinski D, Johnson C, Bayly P, Weaver J, Paulsen

Κ

Physics in Medicine and Biology | 10.1088/1361-6560/ab9a84

2020 Estimation of anisotropic material properties of soft tissue by MRI of ultrasound-induced shear waves

Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Ireland J, Pacia C, Garbow JR, Chen H, Bayly PV

Journal of Biomechanical Engineering | 10.1115/1.4046127

2020 Multi-excitation MR elastography of the brain: wave propagation in anisotropic white matter

Smith D, Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Romano A, Bayly PV, Johnson CL

Journal of Biomechanical Engineering | 10.1115/1.4046199

2018 Mechanical properties of porcine brain tissue in vivo and ex vivo estimated by MR elastography

Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Schmidt JL, Badachhape AA, Johnson CL, Bayly PV

Journal of Biomechanics | 10.1016/j.jbiomech.2018.01.016

2017 Validation of single c-arm fluoroscopic technique for measuring in vivo abdominal wall deformation

Kahan LG, Guertler C, Blatnik JA, Lake SP

Journal of Biomechanical Engineering | 10.1115/1.4037073

2015 Patterned compliance in robotic finger pads for versatile surface usage in dexterous manipulation

Bullock IM, Guertler C, Dollar AM

IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation | 10.1109/ICRA.2015.7139545

2013 Grasp frequency and usage in daily household and machine shop tasks

Bullock IM, Zheng JZ, De La Rosa S, Guertler C, Dollar AM *IEEE Transactions on Haptics* | 10.1109/TOH.2013.6

2012 Mushy-layer dynamics in micro and hyper gravity

O'Rourke JG, Riggs AJE, Guertler CA, Miller PW, Padhi CM, Popelka MM, Wells AJ, West AC, Zhong J, Wettlaufer

JS

Physics of fluids | 10.1063/1.4760256

## **Patents**

2018 Store-Easy Automotive wheelchair storage device.

Patent US9937088B2

Guertler C, D'Souza AW, Milgrom R, Hong T, Xiao Y, Nadell S

2009 Method and System for Treating Hypotension.

Patent US20110098580 Mikhail M and Guertler C

## Awards

2016 Imaging Sciences Pathway Fellowship

2016 First Place (StoreEasy Wheelchair Storage Device) - Bio Entrepreneurship Core's Bench to Business

2015 Sling Health Demo Day Finalist

2013 Connecticut Space Grant College Consortium Student Project Grant

	<u> </u>	
Salactad	Contaranca	<b>Presentations</b>
I S C I C C C C C C	Connerence	riesentations

Selected	Conference Presentations	
2021	Imaging of focused ultrasound-induced shear waves to probe mechanical anisotropy of tissue. Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Garbow JR, Chen H, Bayly PV Design of Medical Devices	
2020	Multi-Excitation methods for MR Elastography of the in vivo porcine brain Guertler CA, Crandall CL, Okamoto RJ, Johnson CL, Bayly PV Summer Biomechanics, Bioengineering, and Biotransport	
2019	Estimation of anisotropic material properties by MRI of ultrasound-induced waves Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Garbow JR, Chen H, Bayly PV Society of Engineering Science	
2018	Contributions of shear and tensile anisotropy to mechanical properties of the porcine brain estimated by MR elastography Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Johnson CL, Bayly PV World Congress of Biomechanics	
2017	Mechanical Properties of Porcine Brain Tissue <i>In Vivo</i> and <i>Ex Vivo</i> Estimated by MR Elastography Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Schmidt JL, Badachhape AA, Johnson CL, Bayly PV Summer Biomechanics, Bioengineering, and Biotransport Conference	
2017	Comparison of Mechanical Properties of Porcine Brain Tissue In Vivo and Ex Vivo using MR Elastography Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Schmidt JL, Badachhape AA, Johnson CL, Bayly PV International Society for Magnetic Resonance in Medicine	
2016	Diffusion Tensor Imaging and MR Elastography of the Mini-Pig Brain In Vivo Guertler CA, Okamoto RJ, Cerjanic A, McGarry M, Johnson CL, Bayly PV Biomedical Engineering Society	
2011	Mushy Layer Dynamics in Micro and Hyper Gravity O'Rourke JG, Riggs AJE, Guertler CA, Miller PW, Padhi CM, Popelka MM, Wells AJ, West AC, Zhong J, Wettlaufer JS Physics of Fluids Conference	
Activities	and Leadership	
2020	Designer and Volunteer  Maker Task Force, Washington University in St. Louis/Barnes Jewish Hospital Designed and produced over 1,000 face shields and other PPE equipment to address COVID-19 hospital shortages	
2019-pres.	Volunteer Trained certified therapy dog and volunteer at local hospitals and schools	
2017-19	Chief Operations Officer  Board member in charge of organizing and running design reviews for student projects, mentoring students in design, fabrication, and presentation, establishing biotech and healthcare mentors, and managing Sling Health operations	
2015-17	Facilities Manager Sling Health, student-run biotechnology incubator Supervisor of facilities used by team members	
2014	Project Leader  Sling Health, student-run biotechnology incubator Team lead designing and building an automated wheelchair vehicle storage device for manual wheelchair users	
2014-17	Vice President Spectra, Graduate Student Imaging Society Vice president of imaging science program	
2012-14	President Yale NASA Microgravity University President of Yale chapter of NASA Microgravity University	
2011-13	Team Leader Yale NASA Microgravity University	

Project leader of Yale's chapter of NASA Microgravity University

Undergraduate group teaching short courses to middle and high school students

Yale University

2011-14

Splash at Yale

### Extracurricular Projects

2014-17	Project Leader Created and patented device for automated manual wheelchair s	Automotive Wheelchair Storage Device, Sling Health torage
2013	Designer and Fabricator Ear Nose Throat Surgical Device for Yale Medical School Surgeon Low-cost replacement for Da Vinci Robot in the performance of back-of-throat and skull base ENT surgeries	
2013	Designer and Fabricator scale measures objects in 1-5 kg in microgravity conditions	Microgravity Object Scale
2012	Designer and Fabricator Solidification of Fluids and the Formation of Mushy Layers designed zero-G experiment, built experimental rig, and conduct	NASA Microgravity University ed experiment
2011	Designer and Fabricator Behavior of Two-Dimensional Rayleigh-Taylor Instability in Variou	NASA Microgravity University us Gravities

### **Teaching**

2014-17	Outreach Educator   Imaging Science Outreach   St. Louis Science Center
2014-15	Graduate Teaching Assistant   Materials Science Lab   Washington University in St. Louis
2011-14	Lecturer   The Science of Ice Cream   Yale Splash

designed zero-G experiment, built experimental rig, and conducted experiment

### References

Philip V Bayly, PhD
The Lee Hunter Distinguished Professor of Mechanical Engineering
Chair, Mechanical Engineering & Materials Science
Washington University in St. Louis
pvb@wustl.edu; 314-935-6081

Ruth J. Okamoto, DSc.

Teaching Professor Mechanical Engineering & Materials Science Director, Spartan Light Metal Products Makerspace Washington University in St. Louis rjo@wustl.edu; 314-935-6068

Curtis L. Johnson, PhD Assistant Professor Biomedical Engineering University of Delaware cli@udel.edu; 302-831-4098

Joel R. Garbow, PhD Professor of Radiology Washington University in St. Louis garbow@wustl.edu; 314-362-9949

John Chong, PhD Head of Engineering and Product Strategy DeepSight Technology jchong@deepsightinc.com